<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Corporation-credit, or, A bank of credit made currant, by common consent in London More useful and safe than money.</title>
            <author>Murray, Robert, 1635-1725?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51629</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3116</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218165</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829782</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829782</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34225</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51629)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34225)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2010:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Corporation-credit, or, A bank of credit made currant, by common consent in London More useful and safe than money.</title>
                  <author>Murray, Robert, 1635-1725?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by John Gain, for the Ofice,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno, M.DC.LXXXII. [1682]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Robert Murray.</note>
                  <note>Caption title, p. 3: Corporation-credit, or A bank of credit made currant, &amp;c.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Banks and banking --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34225:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Corporation-Credit,</hi> OR, A BANK of CREDIT made Currant, by Common Conſent in <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>More <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful</hi> and <hi>Safe</hi> than <hi>Money.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Gain,</hi> for the Office, <hi>Anno,</hi> M.DC.LXXXII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:34225:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:34225:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Corporation-Credit,</hi> OR <hi>A</hi> Bank of Credit <hi>made Currant,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>VVHereas the Right Honourable, the Lord Mayor, Aldermen, and Commons in Common Council Aſſembled, did refer the Conſideration and Examination of the State of the Chamber of <hi>London,</hi> unto a ſelect Committee of Aldermen and Commons, giving them power to receive all ſuch Propoſitions as ſhould be made by any Perſons for the Improvement of the Revenue of the Chamber.</p>
            <p>And whereas in purſuance thereof the ſaid Committee did take into their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration certain Propoſals which were made for the Erecting of a <hi>Bank of Credit,</hi> which might be made Currant by Common Conſent in <hi>London,</hi> and ſerve in many Caſes to ſupply the want of preſent Money for the better Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and Increaſe of Trade, and be a good meanes alſo to ſecure Traders from thoſe hazards, which common Experience tells us, do ordinarily befall unwary people, when they give Credit to Inſolvent Perſons, as well as it may ſerve to improve the Revenue of the Chamber, if the ſame were reduced into Practice.</p>
            <p>All which being well weighed, ſeriouſly conſidered, and duly examined by the ſaid Committee on the Behalf of the City, they did agree, That the ſaid Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals ſhould be reduced into Practice and Execution by the Propoſers, ſo as the Books of Accompts, Books of Regiſter, the Iournals, and other Books relating to the ſaid <hi>Bank of Credit</hi> be duly and orderly kept, and Ballanced, that they may be made ſubject at all times to the Care and Inſpection of the Common Council, or of any two or more of ſuch Perſons as ſhall be from time to time by them appointed thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:34225:3"/>And that all <hi>Clarks, Accomptants, Deputies, Agents, Officers</hi> and <hi>Servants,</hi> that ſhall be employed for the reducing of the ſaid Propoſals into Practice, give good Security for the faithful Diſcharge of their Reſpective Places.</p>
            <p>And further, That no Reward or Summe of Money be given or taken, but that the Perſon giving or taking any Summe of Money for any Office in that <hi>Bank of Credit,</hi> ſhall be for ever diſabled to manage or put in Practice any of the ſaid Propoſals.</p>
            <p>All which being mutually agreed unto by, and between the ſaid Committee and the Propoſers. It pleaſed the Right Honorable the Lord Mayor and Court of Aldermen, after ſeveral Debates concerning the Premiſes among themſelves, to conclude and agree that the ſaid Propoſals be put into Practice by ſuch Truſtees as ſhould be thereunto Commiſſionated and appointed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the City of <hi>London,</hi> and Liberties thereof for the Benefit of the Chamber, and the furtherance of Trade there. In Teſtimony whereof they have cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed the Common Seal of the Lord Mayor, Commonalty, and Citizens of <hi>London</hi> to be affixed unto a certain Writing containing the ſaid Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſals and other Articles. Bearing Date at <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> the 29th. day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> in the 34th. Year of the Reign of our Soveraign Lord <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, by the Grace of God, of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> King, Defender of the Faith: And in the Year of Chriſt, 1682.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:34225:3"/>
               <p>NOw for the reducing the ſaid Propoſitions into Practice, divers Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and other Perſons of Honour and Intereſt, many Conſiderable and Wealthy Citizens and Inhabitants of <hi>London,</hi> as well Merchants as others, (although they ſtand not in need of Money or Credit from the <hi>Bank</hi>) yet they knowing well that no mans Credit ought to be larger than his Eſtate. And that it will be as neceſſary to have a Common Meaſure or Standard in the <hi>Bank of Credit,</hi> for the Tryal of Credit, as it is to have Weights and Meaſures of Standard Aſſize kept in every Ware-houſe or Shop, for the meaſuring and weighing of Goods, and the Preſervation of Commutative Juſtice between Man and Man.</p>
               <p>And having further conſidered alſo that the Summe of Money they or any man elſe have Subſcribed, or do intend to Subſcribe as his and their Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Credit in the <hi>Bank,</hi> is, and will be within his and their own Power, and at his and their own Pleaſure at all times hereafter to increaſe or dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, alter and transfer, as he or they ſhall think fit, according to Emergency of Trade; as much as it is in the Power and Pleaſure of any Man to increaſe or diminiſh the number of Weights and Meaſures in his own Ware-houſe or Shop. And they having further conſidered that although by this meanes any man may know the Currency of another mans Credit, yet no man can diſcover thereby the Ballance of another mans Eſtate.</p>
               <p>Therefore they have been pleaſed in the firſt place to Subſcribe ſeveral Summs of Money which they will cauſe to be brought in as a Fund or Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Honour, either in <hi>Engliſh Tin,</hi> or <hi>Lead, Copper, Steel,</hi> or <hi>Iron, Raw Silk, Wool,</hi> or <hi>Cotton,</hi> or in <hi>Braſs</hi> or <hi>Iron Wyre, Linnen-Cloth</hi> or <hi>Callicoes,</hi> or in ſome other Goods of ſufficient value to raiſe the Summe of Money by them Subſcribed, and to cauſe the ſame to be brought into the Ware-houſe belonging to the <hi>Bank of Credit,</hi> on, or before the firſt day of <hi>January</hi> next enſuing, or within one Week next after notice ſhall be given them of the day when the <hi>Bank of Credit</hi> ſhall be open: and to continue the ſame there, or ſome other Goods in their Place, of the ſame, or of a greater value, for the full Term of one whole Year, paying for the uſe of the ſaid Credit, Ware-houſe Room, Salvage and Book-keeping of, or upon the ſaid Goods or Wares, after the Rate of 6 <hi>
                     <abbr>l.</abbr> per Cent. per Annum,</hi> for the firſt Year.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly.</hi> All ſuch Perſons as have more Goods than their own Ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe can contain; and all ſuch as deſire to have their Goods ſecured againſt the danger of Fire, and hazard of Thieves, may depoſit them in the Ware-houſe of this <hi>Bank,</hi> where they ſhall have Ware-houſe-Room, if they be not too Bulky, and be ſecured againſt thoſe Hazards, paying only 2 <hi>
                     <abbr>l.</abbr> per Cent.</hi> for Ware-houſe-Room and Salvage, according to the value of the ſaid Goods, as they were apprayſed when they were taken in.</p>
               <p>But in caſe any Perſon compriſed under this Article ſhall deſire to make uſe of <hi>Bank-Credit</hi> for the ſaid Goods, or any part thereof, then there ſhall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34225:4"/>
be paid four <hi>per Cent.</hi> further for the uſe of the <hi>Bank-Credit</hi> by them em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly.</hi> All Credible Perſons who have more Goods, Wares, or Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizes by them than they have preſent uſe or Market for, may upon the Fund of them, be ſupplyed from the <hi>Bank</hi> with Bills of Currant Credit, which may be as uſeful, and more ſafe than Money, to ſerve their Occaſions and Emergencies of Trade.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly.</hi> All Perſons that have received any <hi>Bank-Credit,</hi> may transfer the ſame, or any part thereof to whom they pleaſe. And all Perſons to whom ſuch <hi>Bank-Credit</hi> ſhall be tendred, may be well aſſured at the <hi>Bank</hi> of the Currancy of that Credit which hath a good Foundation there, where it ſhall from time to time be accepted and taken in diſcharge of any Debt, as well as in the Releaſe of Goods.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly.</hi> If any Subſcriber or other Perſon that hath received more <hi>Bank-Credit</hi> than he hath occaſion for at the preſent, he may be directed at the <hi>Bank</hi> how to diſpoſe thereof with profit, by transferring the ſame unto others upon valuable Conſideration, and to have Money for the ſame if it be required.</p>
               <p>This being the true Conſtitution of the <hi>Bank of Credit,</hi> it will be the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> of every man of Credit in his Trade, to have his Name, and ſome <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est</hi> therein. But ſuch as either have no Credit, or deſerve none, becauſe they can depoſit no <hi>Fund,</hi> may ſpeak againſt it, and ſhun the <hi>Bank,</hi> becauſe it is a <hi>Touchſtone,</hi> as the Workers in falſe and counterfeit Metal will ſhun the Aſſay and Tryal.</p>
               <p>And although ſome others who have taken unconſcionable Rates for the Loan and Procuration of Money, may be angry, becauſe they muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with leſs Gaines: yet will this <hi>Bank of Credit</hi> be found to be a great benefit unto Trade, and recommend it ſelf to the Judgment, Approbation, and uſage of every unbiaſſed man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="notice">
               <head>Advertiſement.</head>
               <p>ALL Perſons that are deſirous to Subſcribe, may come either to <hi>Garro-way</hi>'s, <hi>Jonathan</hi>'s, <hi>Kemp</hi>'s, or the <hi>Amſterdam</hi> Coffee-Houſes near the <hi>Exchange:</hi> to the <hi>Rainbow,</hi> or to <hi>Richard</hi>'s Coffee-houſe near <hi>Temple-Bar: Peter</hi>'s Coffee-houſe in <hi>Covent-Garden:</hi> and <hi>Man</hi>'s Coffee-houſe at <hi>Charing-Croſs:</hi> at all which Places Books ſhall lye ready, and Perſons attend from Ten to Twelve in the Morning, and from Five to Seven in the Evening eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Week-day for that Purpoſe, and to anſwer Objections, if there be any made by ſuch as do not underſtand, or are not ſo well ſatisfied about the Uſefulneſs and Advantages of the <hi>Bank of Credit</hi> unto all as the ſame is ſet forth in a Printed Paper, called, <hi>Englands Intereſt, On the great Benefit to Trade, by Banks or Offices of Credit in</hi> London.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:34225:4"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
